I work with a species called "Bonobo."
انا اعمل مع نوع يدعى بونوبو.
And I'm happy most of the time,
وأنا سعيدة معظم الوقت،
because I think this is the happiest species on the planet.
لأني أعتقد أنها أسعد مخلوقات على الكوكب.
It's kind of a well-kept secret.
انه ذلك النوع من السر الذي تم كتمه.
This species lives only in the Congo.
هذه الأنواع تعيش فقط في الكونغو.
And they're not in too many zoos, because of their sexual behavior.
ولا تتواجد في حدائق حيوانات كثيرة، بسبب سلوكهم الجنسي.
Their sexual behavior is too human-like
فهو أقرب كثيرا لسلوك الإنسان الجنسي
for most of us to be comfortable with.
لكي يشعر معظمنا بالراحة لهذا الأمر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But --
ولكن --
actually, we have a lot to learn from them, because they're a very
حقيقة، لديهم الكثير مما يمكننا ان نتعلمه منهم، لانهم
egalitarian society and they're a very empathetic society.
مجتمع مساواة وحنون جدا.
And sexual behavior is not confined to one aspect of their life
سلوكهم الجنسي ليس مجرد جانب واحد من جوانب حياتهم
that they sort of set aside.
والذي يمكن وضعه جانبا.
It permeates their entire life.
انه يتخلل كل جوانب حياتهم.
And it's used for communication.
ويستخدم في التواصل.
And it's used for conflict resolution.
وفي حل النزاعات.
And I think perhaps somewhere in our history we sort of,
وأعتقد انه ربما في وقت ما من تاريخنا، نوعا ما
divided our lives up into lots of parts.
قد قسمنا حياتنا لأجزاء كثيرة.
We divided our world up with lots of categories.
قسمنا عالمنا لفئات كثيرة.
And so everything sort of has a place that it has to fit.
وبالتالي كل شيء له مكانه المناسب.
But I don't think that we were that way initially.
ولكني لا أعتقد اننا كنا هكذا في البداية.
There are many people who think that the animal world is hard-wired
هناك الكثيرون الذين يعتقدون ان عالم الحيوان مكان صعب دخوله
and that there's something very, very special about man.
وأن هناك شيء مميز جدا جدا بخصوص الإنسان.
Maybe it's his ability to have causal thought.
ربما قدرته على التفكير السببي.
Maybe it's something special in his brain
ربما هو شيء مميز في مخه
that allows him to have language.
يجعله يستطيع تحدث اللغة
that allows him to make tools or to have mathematics.
يجعله يستطيع صنع الأدوات وفهم الرياضيات.
Well, I don't know. There were Tasmanians who were discovered
حسنا، أنا لا أعرف. كان هناك بشر في تسمانيا أكتشفوا
around the 1600s and they had no fire.
في القرن السابع عشر ولم يكن لديهم نار.
They had no stone tools.
لم يكن لديهم أدوات حجرية.
To our knowledge they had no music.
حسب معرفتنا لم يكن لديهم موسيقى.
So when you compare them to the Bonobo,
ولذا فإننا عندما نقارنهم بالبونوبو،
the Bonobo is a little hairier.
البونوبو اكثر شعرا قليلا.
He doesn't stand quite as upright.
لا يقف بصورة مستقيمة تماما.
But there are a lot of similarities.
ولكن هناك الكثير من التشابه.
And I think that as we look at culture,
وأنا اعتقد انه إذا نظرنا لمفهوم الثقافات،
we kind of come to understand
سنفهم نوعا ما
how we got to where we are.
كيف وصلنا لما نحن عليه.
And I don't really think it's in our biology;
وأنا لا أعتقد أنه شيء في تركيبنا الحيوي،
I think we've attributed it to our biology,
أعتقد أننا قمنا بزرعه في تركيبنا الحيوي،
but I don't really think it's there.
ولكني لا أعتقد انه كان موجودا أصلا.
So what I want to do now is introduce you
وان ما سأفعله الآن هو أني سأعرفكم
to a species called the Bonobo.
على مخلوقات تدعى بونوبو.
This is Kanzi.
هذا كانزي.
He's a Bonobo.
هو من البونوبو.
Right now, he's in a forest in Georgia.
حاليا، هو يعيش في غابة في جورجيا.
His mother originally came from a forest in Africa.
أمه جاءت أصلا من غابة في أفريقيا.
And she came to us when she was just at puberty,
وقد جاءت الينا في بدايات سن بلوغها.
about six or seven years of age.
كان عمرها حوالي ست أو سبع سنوات.
Now this shows a Bonobo on your right,
هنا يوجد هيكل بونوبو على يمينكم،
and a chimpanzee on your left.
وشمبانزي على شمالكم.
Clearly, the chimpanzee has a little bit harder time of walking.
من الواضح أن الشمبانزي يواجه صعوبة بعض الشيء في المشي.
The Bonobo, although shorter than us and their arms still longer,
البونوبو، على الرغم من قصرهم بالنسبة إلينا، وأيديهم الطويلة،
is more upright, just as we are.
ولكنهم أكثر أستقامة، مثلنا تماما.
This shows the Bonobo compared to an australopithecine like Lucy.
هذا يوضح البونوبو مقارنة مع أسترالوبيثين مثل لوسي.
As you can see, there's not a lot of difference
كما ترون لا يوجد الكثير من الفروق،
between the way a Bonobo walks
بين طريقة مشي البونوبو
and the way an early australopithecine would have walked.
والطريقة التي قد يمكن أن يمشي بها الأسترالوبيثين.
As they turn toward us you'll see
و عندما يستديرون باتجاهنا، سترون
that the pelvic area of early australopithecines is a little flatter
أن منطقة الحوض في الأسترالوبيثين البدائي مسطحة قليلا
and doesn't have to rotate quite so much from side to side.
ولا تحتاج ان تديرها من جانب لجانب كثيرا.
So the -- the bipedal gait is a little easier.
وبالتالي فأن المشي ثنائي الأطراف أكثر سهولة.
And now we see all four.
والأن سنرى الأربعة.
Video: Narrator: The wild Bonobo lives in central Africa, in the jungle
فيديو: البونوبو البرية تعيش في وسط أفريقيا، في الغابة
encircled by the Congo River.
محاطة دائريا بنهر الكونغو.
Canopied trees as tall as 40 meters, 130 feet,
الأشجار الكانوبية الكثيفة، طولها 40 متر، 130 قدم،
grow densely in the area.
تنمو هناك بكثافة.
It was a Japanese scientist
كانت عالمة يابانية
who first undertook serious field studies of the Bonobo,
اول من قام بدراسة ميدانية حقيقية حول البونوبو،
almost three decades ago.
منذ ثلاثة عقود تقريبا.
Bonobos are built slightly smaller than the chimpanzee.
البونوبو ذات بنية أصغر قليلا من الشمبانزي.
Slim-bodied, Bonobos are by nature very gentle creatures.
أجسامها نحيلة، البونوبو بحكم طبيعتها كائنات لطيفة جدا.
Long and careful studies have reported many new findings on them.
دراسات طويلة ودقيقة أكتشفت أشياء كثيرة عنهم.
One discovery was that wild Bonobos often walk bidpedally.
مثلا أن البونوبو البرية غالبا ما يمشون على قدمين فقط.
What's more, they are able to walk upright for long distances.
وأيضا، يمكنهم أن يمشوا بطريقة مستقيمة لمسافات طويلة.
Susan Savage-Rumbaugh (video): Let's go say hello to Austin first and then go to the A frame.
لنذهب نلقي التحية على أوستين، ومن بعدها للخيمة.
SS: This is Kanzi and I, in the forest.
سوزان: هذا هو أنا وكانزي في الغابة.
None of the things you will see in this particular video are trained.
لا شيء مما سترونه في هذا الفيديو تم التدرب عليه مسبقا.
None of them are tricks.
لا يوجد أي خدع.
They all happened to be captured on film spontaneously,
تم تصويرهم بطريقة عفوية.
by NHK of Japan.
بواسطة هيئة الأذاعة اليابانية.
We have eight Bonobos.
لدينا ثمانية بونوبو.
Video: Look at all this stuff that's here for our campfire.
فيديو: أنظر لكل هذه الأشياء التي لدينا في المعسكر.
SS: An entire family at our research centre.
سوزان: عائلة كاملة تعيش في مركز أبحاثنا.
Video: You going to help get some sticks?
فيديو: هل ستساعدني في جلب بعض الحطب؟
Good.
جيد.
We need more sticks, too.
نحتاج للمزيد من الحطب.
I have a lighter in my pocket if you need one.
لدي قداحة في جيبي إذا كنت تحتاج واحدة.
That's a wasps' nest.
هذا عش زنابير.
You can get it out.
يمكنك إخراجها.
I hope I have a lighter.
أرجو أن يكون لدي قداحة.
You can use the lighter to start the fire.
يمكنك إشعال النار بالقداحة.
SS: So Kanzi is very interested in fire.
سوزان: كانزي مهتم جدا بالنار.
He doesn't do it yet without a lighter,
لا يمكنه إشعالها بدون قداحة بعد،
but I think if he saw someone do it, he might be able to do --
ولكني أعتقد أنه إذا رآى احدهم يفعلها، فسيمكنه --
make a fire without a lighter.
إشعال النار بدون قداحة.
He's learning about how to keep a fire going.
إنه يتعلم كيفية الإبقاء على النار مشتعلة.
He's learning the uses for a fire,
يتعلم إستخدامات النار،
just by watching what we do with fire.
فقط بمشاهدة ماذا نفعل نحن بها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is a smile on the face of a Bonobo.
هذه إبتسامة على وجه بونوبو.
These are happy vocalizations.
هذه أصوات سعادة.
Video: You're happy.
فيديو: أنت سعيد.
You're very happy about this part.
أنت سعيد جدا بخصوص هذا الجزء.
You've got to put some water on the fire. You see the water?
يجب عليك وضع بعض الماء على النار. أترى الماء؟
Good job.
عمل جيد.
SS: Forgot to zip up the back half of his backpack.
سوزان: لقد نسيت ان أغلق الجزء الخلفي من حقيبة ظهره.
But he likes to carry things from place to place.
ولكنه يحب ان يحمل الأشياء من مكان لاخر.
Video: Austin, I hear you saying "Austin."
فيديو: أوستين، أسمعك تقول أوستين.
SS: He talks to other Bonobos at the lab, long-distance,
سوزان: يستطيع التحدث مع بونوبو آخرين في المختبر،
farther than we can hear.
من مسافات أبعد مما نستطيع ان نسمع.
This is his sister.
هذه هي اخته.
This is her first time to try to drive a golf cart.
هذه هي محاولتها الأولى لقيادة عربة جولف.
Video: Goodbye.
فيديو: مع السلامة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
SS: She's got the pedals down, but not the wheel.
سوزان: إنها تضغط على البدال، ولكنها لا تدير العجلة.
She switches from reverse to forward
تغير من الإتجاه الخلفي للأمام
and she holds onto the wheel, rather than turns it.
وتتمسك بالعجلة أكثر من محاولة إدارتها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Like us, she knows that that individual in the mirror is her.
مثلنا تماما، تعرف أن ذاك الوجه في المرآة هو وجهها.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Video: Narrator: By raising Bonobos in a culture that is both Bonobo and human,
فيديو: بتربية البونوبو في بيئة مشتركة بين بيئة البونوبو والإنسان،
and documenting their development across two decades,
وبتوثيق تطورهم على مدى عقدين،
scientists are exploring how cultural forces
اكتشف العلماء كيف أمكن للقوى الثقافية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
may have operated during human evolution.
أن تساهم في تطور الإنسان.
His name is Nyota.
أسمه نيوتا.
It means "star" in Swahili.
وتعني "نجم" بالسواحيلي.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Panbanisha is trying to give Nyota a haircut with a pair of scissors.
بانبانيشا تحاول ان تقص شعر نيوتا بالمقص.
In the wild, the parent Bonobo is known to groom its offspring.
في البرية، من المعروف ان البونوبو تزين أبنائها.
Here Panbanisha uses scissors, instead of her hands,
هنا بانبانيشا تستخدم المقص بدلا من يديها،
to groom Nyota.
لتزيين نيوتا.
Very impressive.
مثير للاعجاب.
Subtle maneuvering of the hands is required
التحكم الجيد في حركة اليدين مطلوب
to perform delicate tasks like this.
للقيام بالمهمات الحساسة كهذه.
Nyota tries to imitate Panbanisha by using the scissors himself.
نيوتا يحاول تقليد بانبانيشا بإستخدام المقص بنفسه.
Realizing that Nyota might get hurt,
بأدراك أن نيوتا قد يجرح نفسه،
Panbanisha, like any human mother,
بانبانيشا مثل أي أم بشرية،
carefully tugs to get the scissors back.
تحاول بحرص أخذ المقص.
He can now cut through tough animal hide.
يمكنه الآن أن يقطع الغطاء عن ذلك البرطمان.
SS: Kanzi's learned to make stone tools.
سوزان: كانزي تعلم كيف يصنع أدوات حجرية.
Video: Kanzi now makes his tools,
فيديو: كانزي الآن يمكنه صنع أدواته بنفسه،
just as our ancestors may have made them,
تماما كما أستطاع الأقدمون صناعتها،
two-and-a-half million years ago --
منذ ما يقرب من مليونين ونصف من الأعوام --
by holding the rocks in both hands, to strike one against the other.
بأمساك حجر في كل يد، وكحتهما مقابل بعضهما.
He has learned that by using both hands
لقد تعلم انه بإستخدام يديه الأثنتين
and aiming his glancing blows,
وأستخدام ضربات خاطفة وسريعة،
he can make much larger, sharper flakes.
يمكنه صنع رقائق أكثر ضخامة وحدة.
Kanzi chooses a flake he thinks is sharp enough.
كانزي يختار الرقاقة التي يظن أنها حادة كفاية.
The tough hide is difficult to cut, even with a knife.
من الصعب قطع الغطاء، حتى بسكين.
The rock that Kanzi is using is extremely hard
الصخرة التي يستخدمها كانزي قاسية جدا
and ideal for stone tool making, but difficult to handle,
مثالية كأداة حجرية، ولكن صعبة التعامل،
requiring great skill.
تتطلب مهارة كبيرة.
Kanzi's rock is from Gona, Ethiopia
صخرة كانزي من جونا، أثيوبيا
and is identical to that used by our African ancestors
ومشابهة تماما للتي كان يستخدمها أجدادنا الأفارقة
two-and-a-half million years ago.
منذ مليونين ونصف من الأعوام.
These are the rocks Kanzi used
هذه هي الصخور التي أستعملها كانزي
and these are the flakes he made.
وهذه الرقائق التي صنعها.
The flat sharp edges are like knife blades.
الأسطح الحادة المسطحة تشبه انصال السكاكين.
Compare them to the tools our ancestors used;
مقارنة بما كان يستعمله أجدادنا،
they bear a striking resemblance to Kanzi's.
فأنه يوجد تشابه غريب لما صنعه كانزي.
Panbanisha is longing to go for a walk in the woods.
بانبانيشا تتلهف للخروج في جولة للغابة.
She keeps staring out the window.
تظل محدقة عبر النافذة للخارج.
SS: This is -- let me show you something we didn't think they would do.
سوزان: هذا.. دعوني أريكم شيئا لم نكن نعتقد أنه يمكنهم فعله.
Video: For several days now, Panbanisha has not been outside.
فيديو: لأيام عديدة الآن، بانبانيشا لم تذهب للخارج.
SS: I normally talk about language.
سوزان: دائما ما أتحدث عن اللغة.
Video: Then Panbanisha does something unexpected.
فيديو: ثم فجأة قامت بشيء غير متوقع.
SS: But since I'm advised not to do what I normally do,
سوزان: ولكن بما أني نصحت الا أفعل ما أفعله دائما،
I haven't told you that these apes have language.
لم أخبركم أن هذه القردة لها لغتها الخاصة.
It's a geometric language.
أنها لغة هندسية.
Video: She takes a piece of chalk
فيديو: أنها تأخذ قطعة من الطباشير
and begins writing something on the floor.
وتكتب شيئا ما على الأرض.
What is she writing?
ما الذي تكتبه؟
SS: She's also saying the name of that, with her voice.
سوزان: إنها أيضا تقول اسمه بصوتها.
Video: Now she comes up to Dr. Sue and starts writing again.
فيديو: الأن تأتي لدكتور سو وتكتب ثانية.
SS: These are her symbols on her keyboard.
سوزان:ما ترسمه هو رموز خاصة بلوحة مفاتيحها.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
They speak when she touches them.
الرموز تصدر أصواتا عندما تلمسها.
Video: Panbanisha is communicating to Dr. Sue where she wants to go.
فيديو: بانبانيشا تخبر دكتور سو عن المكان الذي تريد الذهاب إليه.
"A frame" represents a hut in the woods.
هذا الرمز يمثل كوخ في الغابة.
Compare the chalk writing with the lexigram on the keyboard.
مقارنة بما كتبته بالطبشور مع الرموز على اللوحة.
Panbanisha began writing the lexigrams on the forest floor.
بانبانيشا تبدأ في كتابة الرمز على الأرضية.
SS (video): Very nice. Beautiful, Panbanisha.
رائع جدا. جميل، يا بانبانيشا.
SS: At first we didn't really realize what she was doing,
سوزان: بداية لم نكن ندرك ما الذي كانت تفعله.
until we stood back and looked at it and rotated it.
حتى نظرنا إليها من بعيد بعد تدويرها.
Video: This lexigram also refers to a place in the woods.
فيديو: هذا الرمز يرمز أيضا إلى مكان في الغابة.
The curved line is very similar to the lexigram.
الخط المنحني مشابه جدا للرمز.
The next symbol Panbanisha writes represents "collar."
الرمز الثاني الذي ترسمه بانبانيشا يمثل طوق.
It indicates the collar that Panbanisha must wear when she goes out.
إنه يمثل الطوق الذي يجب أن تلبسه بانبانيشا حين تذهب للخارج.
SS: That's an institutional requirement.
سوزان: هذا من متطلبات المؤسسة.
Video: This symbol is not as clear as the others,
فيديو: هذا الرمز غير واضح كالأخرين،
but one can see Panbanisha is trying to produce a curved line
ولكن بمجرد رؤية بانبانيشا تحاول ان ترسم خط منحن
and several straight lines.
وعدة خطوط مستقيمة.
Researchers began to record what Panbanisha said,
بدأ الباحثون في تسجيل ما قالته بانبانيشا،
by writing lexigrams on the floor with chalk.
بكتابة الرموز على الأرض بالطباشير.
Panbanisha watched.
وبانبانيشا تشاهد.
Soon she began to write as well.
سرعان ما بدأت بانبانيشا في الكتابة أيضا.
The Bonobo's abilities have stunned scientists around the world.
قدرات البونوبو أذهلت العلماء حول العالم.
How did they develop?
كيف تطوروا؟
SS (video): We found that the most important thing
سوزان: لقد وجدنا أن أهم شيء
for permitting Bonobos to acquire language is not to teach them.
لكي نسمح للبونوبو بتعلم اللغة ليس أن نعلمهم إياها.
It's simply to use language around them,
ولكن ببساطة ان نستخدمها حولهم،
because the driving force in language acquisition
لأن القوة الدافعة لإمتلاك اللغة
is to understand what others, that are important to you, are saying to you.
هي في فهم ما يقوله الأخرون - المهمون لك- لك انت.
Once you have that capacity,
بمجرد أمتلاكك تلك القدرة،
the ability to produce language
قابلية أن تنتج لغة
comes rather naturally and rather freely.
تكون اكثر طبيعية و حرة.
So we want to create an environment in which Bonobos,
لذلك أردنا خلق بيئة حيث يمكن للبونوبو
like all of the individuals with whom they are interacting --
أن تقوم بكل ما يقوم به الأشخاص الذي تتفاعل معهم.
we want to create an environment in which they have fun,
أردنا خلق بيئة حيث يمكن لها أن تمرح،
and an environment in which the others
بيئة يكون فيها الأشخاص من حولهم
are meaningful individuals for them.
ذو أهمية ووجود له معنى.
Narrator: This environment brings out unexpected potential
هذه البيئة توفر أحتمالات لا محدودة
in Kanzi and Panbanisha.
لكل من كانزي وبانبانيشا.
Panbanisha is enjoying playing her harmonica,
بانبانيشا تستمتع بالعزف على الهارمونيكا،
until Nyota, now one year old, steals it.
حتى جاء يوتا ،الذي بلغ السنة من عمره، وسرقها.
Then he peers eagerly into his mother's mouth.
ثم أخذ ينظر بحرص وفضول لفم أمه.
Is he looking for where the sound came from?
إنه يتساءل: من أين يأتي هذا الصوت؟
Dr. Sue thinks it's important to allow such curiosity to flourish.
دكتور سو تعتقد انه مهم جدا ان ندع هذا الفضول ينمو ويزدهر.
This time Panbanisha is playing the electric piano.
الآن تلعب بانبانيشا بالبيانو الكهربائي.
She wasn't forced to learn the piano;
لم تجبر على لعبه أو تعلمه،
she saw a researcher play the instrument and took an interest.
ولكنها شاهدت الباحثين يعزفون عليها فأخذها الفضول.
Researcher: Go ahead. Go ahead. I'm listening.
أستمري، أستمري، أنا استمع.
Do that real fast part that you did. Yeah, that part.
أعزفي ذلك المقطع السريع الذي عزفته قبل، نعم هذا الجزء.
Narrator: Kanzi plays the xylophone;
كانزي يلعب على الزيليفون،
using both hands he enthusiastically accompanies Dr. Sue's singing.
بأستخدام كلتا يديه وبكل حيوية يصاحب دكتور سو في الغناء.
Kanzi and Panbanisha
كانزي وبانبانيشا
are stimulated by this fun-filled environment,
تم تحفيزهم من خلال تلك البيئة المرحة،
which promotes the emergence of these cultural capabilities.
والتي ساعدت على إظهار تلك القدرات الثقافية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Researcher: OK, now get the monsters. Get them.
حسنا، أمسك بالوحوش الآن، أمسك بهم.
Take the cherries too.
تناول الكرز أيضا.
Now watch out, stay away from them now.
أحذر الآن، أبتعد عنهم الآن.
Now you can chase them again. Time to chase them.
الآن يمكنك مطاردتهم مجددا، حان وقت مطاردتهم
Now you have to stay away. Get away.
الآن يجب عليك أن تبتعد عنهم، أبتعد.
Run away. Run.
أهرب بعيدا، أهرب.
Now we can chase them again. Go get them.
الآن طاردهم، طاردهم.
Oh no!
أوه كلا!
Good Kanzi. Very good. Thank you so much.
أحسنت يا كانزي، جيد جدا. شكرا جزيلا لك.
Narrator: None of us, Bonobo or human, can possibly even imagine?
هل يستطيع أحد منا، بشر كنا أو بونوبو، أن يتخيل؟
SS: So we have a bi-species environment, we call it a "panhomoculture."
سوزان: لدينا هنا بيئة ثنائية النوع، تسمى بيئة بانوبشرية.
We're learning how to become like them.
نتعلم كيف نصبح مثلهم.
We're learning how to communicate with them,
نتعلم كيف نتواصل معهم،
in really high-pitched tones.
عن طريق نغمات صوتية عالية فعلا.
We're learning that they probably have a language in the wild.
نتعلم أنه من المحتمل ان يكون لهم لغتهم الخاصة في البرية.
And they're learning to become like us.
وهم يتعلمون كيف يصبحوا مثلنا.
Because we believe that it's not biology; it's culture.
لأننا نؤمن أنه ليست البيولوجيا ما يجعلنا مختلفين، ولكن الثقافة.
So we're sharing tools and technology and language
ولذلك نحن نتشارك الأدوات والتكنولوجيا واللغة
with another species.
مع أنواع آخرى.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.